<div>
<h3 >Cookie Law Compliance &amp; E-Privacy Directive</h3>
                <p>
                    This site uses some unobtrusive cookies to store information on your computer. Some cookies
                    on this site are essential, and the site won't work as expected without them. These cookies are
                    set when you submit a form, login or interact with the site by doing something that goes beyond
                    clicking on simple links. We also use some non-essential cookies to anonymously track visitors
                    or enhance your experience of the site.
                </p>
                <p><b>To comply with the e-Privacy Directive, we need to ask for your consent to set these cookies.</b></p>

                <button onclick="agree()">I agree</button>
                <button onclick="cancel()">No thanks</button>

                <h2 style="margin-top:2em">More about cookies</h2>
                <p>
                    Cookies that may be used by this website are used either solely on a per session basis or to maintain
                    login and other preferences. Cookies are not shared with any third parties.
                </p>

                <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="4" style="margin:0 2em">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th scope="col">Cookie Name</th>
                            <th scope="col">Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>allowCookies</td>
                            <td>Cookie that confirms that you agree that this site can read/write cookies in your browser.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                __utma<br/>
                                __utmb<br/>
                                __utmc<br/>
                                __utmz<br/>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                            <p>Google Analytics: We use Google Analytics to monitor traffic levels, search queries and visits to this website.</p>
                            <p>Google Analytics stores IP address anonymously on its servers in the US, and your IP address is not associated with any personally identifiable information.</p>
                            <p>These cookies enable Google to determine whether you are a return visitor to the site, and to track the pages that you visit during your session.<br />
                            </p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                      
                        <tr>
                            <td>JSESSIONID</td>
                            <td>
                                <p>
                                    This is a simple token used by Java applications to identify your unique session on the website.
                                    Typically used to maintain the integrity of your session while transacting information with a website
                                    (accessing secure areas, forms submissions etc)
                                </p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
</div>